A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Audiovisual materials FA750
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Ford Foundation Films, 1
  - Gaither and the Ford Foundation Interview
    - Gaither, Silent, black and white, 3 minutes. (Reel AV 2239)
    - Gaither, Silent, Black and white, 9 minutes. (Reel AV 2240)
    - Gaither, Silent, Black and white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2241)
    - Gaither and the Ford Foundation Interview, Silent, black and white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2225)
    - Gaither Ford Foundation 2A, Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes. (Reel AV 2261)
    - Gaither Ford Foundation 2A, Silent, Black and white, 8 minutes. (Reel AV2261)
    - Gaither Interview, Silent, black and white negative, 4 minutes. (Reel AV 2259A, Reel AV 2259B)
    - Gaither Interview, Silent, Black and white negative, 16 minutes. (Reel AV 2260)
    - Gaither Interview, Sound, 3 minutes. (Reel AV 2258A, Reel AV 2258B)
    - Gaither Interview, Sound, black and white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 2263)
    - Gaither Interview, Sound, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1887)
    - Gaither Interview, Silent, Black and white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1886)
    - Gaither Interview, Sound, black and white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 2237)
    - Gaither Varr Descrip, Silentm Black and white, 3 minutes. (Reel AV 2238)
  - Gaon Sathis (Reel AV 2223, Reel AV 2203, Reel AV 2207, Reel AV 1999, Box 2, Dvd AV 1999)
    Film about village life in Allahabad, India and the Gaon Sathis who help improve quality of life in these farming communities with new irrigation methods, agricultural techniques, sanitation and writing. Directed and Produced by Ernest Kleinberg. Copyright 1953.
  - Gasoline Engine (The Otto Cycle), 1951 (Reel AV 1879)
    Short lesson from the College Physics series produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films. Copyright 1951, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - The Great Ideas, 1960s (Reel AV 1810, Reel AV 1809, Reel AV 1783, Reel AV 1782)
    Episodes from the TV series featuring Dr. Mortimer J. Adler, director of the Institute for Philosophical Research, in San Francisco. The doctor explains various aspects of philosophy and responds to viewer questions. Directed by Jim Baker, produced by George Bryson and KGO-TV, San Francisco.
  - Harvest of Energy (Reel AV 1977)
    Study of the biological, social, and environmental effects of rice in the human diet. Includes the production of new varieties, transplant techniques, testing of herbicides, water management, traditional methodologies, and other related criteria.
  - The Haven (Reel AV 1848)
    Short documentary about the emigration of refugee Kalmyk people from Soviet Russia into the United States. Supported by US Government agencies and the Church World Service, a religious group, families were transferred from disparate camps throughout Europe to new settlements in the United States; communities in Philadelphia and New Jersey are profiled in detail. Presented by the United States Information Service, produced by Thomas Craven Film Productions.
  - Hoffman On Tour (Reel AV 1951, Box 2, Dvd AV 1951)
    A promotional film about a world-wide trip by Ford Foundation president Paul Hoffman. Ford administrators traveled the world looking for projects and causes to support. Footage of Mr. Hoffman in India and Hong Kong, and Dr. Robert Hutchins in Berlin. Hoffman speaks of supporting peace, local leadership and combating the rise of Communism.
  - Housing: A Place to Live, 1973 (Reel AV 1871)
    A 2-part documentary about issues of housing, taxes, and inequality in the NY region, including NYC and parts of NJ and CT. This episode is the first in a series of "televised town meetings" designed to face issues within the area and encourage civic dialogue. The series, "Choices for 76", was timed to address challenges and solutions in preparation for the Bicentennial of the USA. The series was presented by the Regional Plan Association in the spring of 1973, which published an accompany text entitled "How to Save Urban America", as well as other newspaper and print articles. Produced by David Sawyer and Albert Waller, in collaboration with the US Department of Housing and Urban Development. Funded by a variety of institutions, including the Ford Foundation, Rockefeller Brothers Fund, the Taconic Foundation and Rockefeller Foundation.
  - Human Reproduction, 1947 (Reel AV 1955)
    A short film explaining the reproductive system and process of birth, through diagrams and illustrations. Correlates to the textbook "Healthful Living" by Dr. Harold S. Diehl. Produced by Audio Productions Inc for the McGraw-Hill Health Education Series. Copyright 1947, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - IFA: Yoruba Divination and Sacrifice (Reel AV 1803)
    An examination of Ifa beliefs within Nigerian communities, which honor water, natural elements, and ancestral spirits. Footage of group prayers, animal sacrifice, and consultation of the natural spirits. Directed by Raymond Price, M.D., of the Section of Transcultural Psychiatric Studies at McGill University. Funded by the Human Ecology Fund, New York.
  - I Just Wanted to Let You Know How Well Rhonda is Doing in School, 1966 (Reel AV 1962)
    Documentation of a 5-year study involving 18 schools throughout California attempting new teaching and administrative methods.
  - The Imprisonment of Obatala (Reel AV 1876)
    A stop-motion film made by children at the New School in Roxbury, CT, as part of the African Art and Culture project. From the Education and Development Center funded by the Ford Foundation.
  - India Awakes, 1956 (Reel AV 2224, Reel AV 1776, Reel AV 2234, Reel AV 2235, Box 2, Dvd AV 2235)
    Film documenting the programs and initiatives developed by the Indian government to improve agriculture, education, health, and general wellbeing throughout the villages and towns of India. Depicts crop research, pest prevention, vaccination, state-run training programs in medicine and farming, and other subjects. Presented by the Ministry of India, Department of Food and Agriculture, produced by the Ford Foundation.
  - Indian Rights, Indian Law, 1978 (Reel AV 1922)
    Edited soundtrack to accompanying unedited footage. Interviews with Native Americans who are fighting to preserve their history and protect their rights. The documentary follows the political struggles borne by Indian communities across the US. Funded by the Ford Foundation, copyright 1978.
  - Indian Rights, Indian Law, 1978; Sound and silent, color, 30 minutes. AV 2255A is A Roll, AV 2255B is B Roll, AV 2255C is header and footer troms with beeping sounds, and AV 2255D is B Wind Soundtrack. (Reel AV 2255A, Reel AV 2255B, Reel AV 2255C, Reel AV 2255D)
    INTERVIEWS WITH NATIVE AMERICANS WHO ARE FIGHTING TO PRESERVE THEIR HISTORY AND PROTECT THEIR RIGHTS. THE DOCUMENTARY FOLLOWS THE POLITICAL STRUGGLES BORNE BY INDIAN COMMUNITIES ACROSS THE US. PRODUCED, DIRECTED and EDITED BY SANDRA and JOSEPH CONSENTINO. FUNDED BY THE FORD FOUNDATION, COPYRIGHT 1978.
  - Indian Rights, Indian Law, 1978; Sound and silent, color, 30 minutes. AV 2256A is soundtrack part I, AV 2256B is internegative optical soundtrack, AV 2256C is A Wind optical soundtrack, and AV 2256D is internegative part II A wind. (Reel AV 2256A, Reel AV 2256B, Reel AV 2256C, Reel AV 2256D)
  - Indian Rights, Indian Law, 1978; Sound and silent, Black & White and Color, 30 minutes. AV 2257A is B Wind Soundtrack, AV 2257B is the title/animation reel, AV 2257C reel 11 of 2, and AV 2257D is B Roll. (Reel AV 2257A, Reel AV 2257B, Reel AV 2257C, Reel AV 2257D)
  - Indonesia, 1958 (Reel AV 2193A, Reel AV 2193C, Reel AV 2193B)
    Lecture 3 of the 15 part "A Changing World in the Light of History" series. Led by Arnold J. Toynbee and presented at Washington and Lee University in Lexington, Virginia. The lecture discusses the history, geography, language, relgion, colonialism, economy, government and current affairs of Indonesia. There is a supplemental question and answer session with the audience after the presentation. Copyright 1958, Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc.
  - Inertial Carts, 1959 (Reel AV 1897)
    An educational short film featuring Dr. Albert P. Little. Presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, copyright 1959, Educational Services Inc.
  - Inertial Mass, 1959 (Reel AV 2213, Reel AV 1849)
  - Investment in Human Progress (Reel AV 2221)
    An introductory history of the Ford Foundation, its trustees and programs during the 1950s given by Henry Ford II and H. Rowan Gaither. Henry Ford II introduces the board of trustees- Frank W. Abrams, James F. Brownlee, John Cowles, Donald K. David, Mark F. Ethridge, Laurence M. Gould, John J. McCloy, Charles Wilson, Charles E. Wyzanski, Jr., H. Rowan Gaither, Jr. and Benson Ford. Clips of "Goan Sathis", "Kennan on Communism" and "Community Leadership Institute" are used as examples of the types of work being done at the Ford Foundation.
  - Investment in Human Progress, A duplicate negative ofone take of an interview. (Reel AV 1997A, Reel AV 1997B)
    Presentation of the Management Meeting Program, FORD MOTOR CO. by Affiliated Film Producers, Inc.
  - In Service Training, 1962-1963 (Reel AV 1963)
    An introductory film about educational television programming for elementary schools. Discussions with a panel of educators planning for their school year
  - Kennan on Communism, 1953 (Reel AV 1990)
    George F. Kennan discusses communism on the Armed Forces Forum in a question and answer session with servicemen. The Q&A is moderated by Frank Blair. Produced and distributed by the United States Army.
  - LAT TCP Excerpts (Reel AV 1423)
    Related Materials
    See: AV 1856.
    Unedited reel of footage examining teacher training, peer tutoring and learning exercises, edited for 1974 Foundation Board meeting.
  - Learning About Thinking and Vice Versa, 1971 (Reel AV 2188, Reel AV 2204, Reel AV 2189)
    Children's thinking processes are demonstrated by educator Eleanor Duckworth through classic Piaget-type interviews held during a workshop for teachers, teacher aides, and principals of two inner-city Philadelphia schools. Developed primarily for teachers and others who deal with children, the film is intended to help deepen understanding of developmental differences in learning. Copyright Ford Foundation, 1971.
  - Learning About Thinking and Vice Versa, 1971; Duplicate negative. (Reel AV 1970A, Reel AV 1970B)
  - Lessons of Sukhmanjri, 1979 (Reel AV 1884)
    Film about the efforts of the Indian Council of Agricultural Research to aid rural farmers. New methods of irrigation and crop management are presented as tools of stabilizing the country. Produced by the Films Division of the Indian Government, copyright 1979.
  - Let's Sing Together (Reel AV 1911)
    An American student group travels to Hungary to study the Kodaly Music training curriculum, along with their teachers and parents. Filmed at the International Studios of Mafium in Budapest and other locations, the film shows the group interacting with Hungarian teachers and students to study and play music together.
  - Light (Reel AV 2005, Reel AV 1996)
    Art film about light and its influence in different environments. Photographed and direct by Manfred Kirchheimer., and produced by Roemer-Young Associates.
  - Living Commitment, 1974 (Reel AV 1870)
    Urban documentary that examines interracial communities and projects throughout the United States, including neighborhood associations in Brooklyn, Connecticut, Los Angeles, and Baltimore. Copyright 1974, National Neighbors.
  - Long Time Intervals, 1960 (Reel AV 1790)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, funded by the National Science Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation. Featuring Professors Harrison Brown, Charles P. McKinney, and Leon T. Silver from the California Institute of Technology. Produced by Educational Services, Inc.
  - A Magnet Laboratory (Reel AV 1994)
    An educational film about electromagnetic force funded by the Natioanl Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools with experimental demonstrations by Professor Francis Bitter, MIT, Dr. John F. Waymouth, Slyvania Electric Products Inc., Evangel Bardho, MIT and Henry H. Kolm Lincoln Laboratories. Produced by Educational Services Incorpated Film Division and Directed by Richard Leacock.
  - The Man in the Middle, 1968 (Reel AV 1894)
    Documentary produced by the New York Police Academy with the John Jay College of Criminal Justice, to demonstrate issues and suggestions for preventing violence and social disruption. Shows real police working in Queens, NY, answering domestic calls and integrating with the community in order to build trust. "Public demonstration is a legal means of affecting social change, speak out". Funded by the Ford Foundation. Copyright 1968, John Jay College.
  - Measurement of the Speed of Light, 1952 (Reel AV 1875)
    Brief educational film from McGraw-Hill Company explaining methods of measuring the speed of light. Diagrams illustrate lessons from Foucault and Michelson. Produced in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1952, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Measuring Large Distances, 1959 (Reel AV 1789)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of its course on physics for secondary schools. With Professor Fletcher G. Watson of Harvard University. Produced by Educational Services Inc.
  - Measuring Small Distances, 1953 (Reel AV 1964)
    An educational film presented by the Physical Science Study Committee, as part of its course on physics for secondary schools. With Professor Dorothy Montgomery of Hollins College, Virginia. Produced by Encyclopedia Brittanica. Copyright, Educational Services Inc.
  - Medbourne Primary School, 1969 (Reel AV 2011, Reel AV 1888)
    A visit to a nontraditional primary school in England that uses innovative programs to support independent development and student leadership. Typical curriculum is replaced with hands-on projects, self-led lessons, outdoors activities, and other innovative methods to empower students. Produced by Henry Felt, in cooperation with the Educational Development Center. Funding from the Public Education of the Ford Foundation.
  - Meeting of the Advisory Committee (Reel AV 1420)
    Unedited silent footage from an undated meeting of a Ford Foundation Committee. Various unidentified talking heads are shown.
  - Movement (Reel AV 1874, Reel AV 2003, Reel AV 1896)
    Seemingly stock footage of motion and movement in nature, architecture, technology, and fine art: leaves in the wind, rushing water, children running and playing, machines in factories, and depictions of movement in paintings and sculptures. FFrom Roemer, Young and Associates.
  - Music Lessons, 1981 (Reel AV 2201, Reel AV 1924)
    An introduction to the Kodaly Method of musical instruction. Elementary students from Connecticut to California are shown learning the basic steps of singing and reading music. Filmed segments of elementary school music education in various cities throughtout the United States. Produced and edited by Joyce Chopra. Copyright 1981, the Ford Foundation.
  - My Brother's Children, 1970 (Reel AV 1891)
    The Family Planning Council of Nigeria presents this dramatized look at efforts to support large families in rural Africa, and suggestions for improving conditions. Villagers balancing farm life, new technologies, and transitions to towns and cities, are education about family planning methods and new health options. Supported by the International Planned Parenthood Federation. Produced by DAN Productions LTD, London.
  - Nationalism, Democracy, Communism, 1958 (Reel AV 2020A, Reel AV 2020C, Reel AV 2020B)
    Lecture 14 of the 15 part "A Changing World in the Light of History" series. Led by Arnold J. Toynbee and presented at Washington and Lee university in Lexington, Virgina. The lecture discusses the topics of nationalism ,democracy and communism on an international scale during the cold war. There is a supplemental question and answer session with the audience after the presentation. Copyright 1958, Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc.
  - New Images: Art in a Changing African Society, 1964 (Reel AV 1961)
    Film discussing the evolution of dance, sculpture, and other traditional fine art practices of the Oshogbo people of Western Nigeria. Made by Francis Speed and Ulli Beier from the University of Ibadan, Nigeria.
  - A New Look at the Sun, 1970 (Reel AV 1419)
    A film about solar physics and the use of a new radio heliograph used to analyze the activity of the sun using radio frequency. The Ford Foundation funded the construction of the Culgoora Radio heliograph, which is featured in the film. Produced by CSIRO Film.
  - New Mathematics in the Primary School, 1959 (Reel AV 1418)
    An educational short film produced by Education Development Center Inc, funded by the Ford Foundation. Documents the lessons and progress of a primary school math program in Nigeria and Tanzania.
  - Non Basta Solo L'alfabeto (Reel AV 2194)
    Documentary film about the work which is carried out by the Center of Adult Education of the Union for the Struggle Against Illiteracy in southern Italy, Saradinia and Sicily. The film highlights literacy, mathematics and vocational training, community upkeep projects, and work to improve local living conditions.
  - The North Carolina Fund (Reel AV 1954)
    Short film from the North Carolina Fund about the poverty cycle: socioeconomic patterns that develop in childhood and continue through adulthood to keep poor populations from succeeding. Funded by the Ford Foundation and others.
  - Nyiregyhazi (Reel AV 1993)
    Documentary on Hungarian born American pianist Ervin Nyiregyhazi recording music for the International Piano Archive funded by a Ford Foundation grant.
  - The Office Telephone (Reel AV 1779)
    Introduction to modern dial telephones, and system of operators and telephone communication in Nigeria. Produced by the Ford Foundation and the Public Authorities of Nigeria, directed by Joseph Franklin.
  - On the Move: Careers in Transportation (Reel AV 1992)
    Careers in Transportation is part of an exploration film series developed by Olympus Research Corporation and the Wyoming State Department of Education in cooperation with the U.S. Office of Education, Division of Manpower Development and Training, Department of Health, Education and Welfare. The film explores the various possible careers connected to transportation.
  - On the Spring Ice, 1975 (Reel AV 1909)
    Film produced by and about the small Eskimo community of Gambell on St. Lawrence Island in Alaska. Shot during the yearly migration of the walrus, the film has footage of village activities, hunting and storing of meat, and other traditions of these Eskimo families. Copyright 1975, the Village of Gambell and Leonard Kemerling.
  - Paper Targets (Reel AV 1987)
    Film by William Flynn, Charles Milson and John Osborne. Original music scored by Larry Johnson. Presented to the Foundation, 1980 July, by the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston in appreciation for the 1974 matching grant for faculty enrichment and student aid.
  - People Without a Place (Reel AV 1784)
    A film about the plight of East German refugees after World War II, told through the story of a young immigrant boy. Written and produced by Ernest Kleinberg.
  - Periodic Motions, 1960 (Reel AV 1787)
    A short educational film with Professors David Ivey and Patterson Hume of the University of Toronto, produced by Educational Services, Inc. Funded by the National Science Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation as part of a course on physics.
  - Photons, 1959 (Reel AV 1417)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Professor John G. King of MIT.
  - Planning Your Family (Reel AV 2197, Reel AV 1921)
    A dramatization of family planning programs in rural Africa. Typical life in a small village is shown, with women and families learning about their reproductive rights and new methods of birth control. Features an Afro-pop theme song about family planning, composed and played by E. K. Mensah. Produced by Anne Balfour-Fraser for the Planned Parenthood Association of Ghana.
  - Principals Conference (Reel AV 1856)
    See: AV 1423.
    Untitled footage from a discussion about a Ford Foundation program to improve schools' communication and performance. Working in multiple grades, the program foocuses on community involvement, in-school tutoring, and teacher reflection and review. Two principals who have implemented the program are interviewed (undated) (see also AV #1423).
  - Principals Conference, Silent and sound, black and white, 14 minutes. AV 2190A is a Positive Master, AV 2190B is a B Positive and AV 2190C is a magnetic soundtrack. (Reel AV 2190A, Reel AV 2190B, Reel AV 2190C)
    Footage from a discussion about a Ford Foundation program to improve school communication and performance. Working in multiple grades, the program focuses on community involvement, in-school tutoring, and teacher reflection and review. Two principals who have implemented the program are interviewed.
  - Progressive Waves, 1953 (Reel AV 1843)
    Film from the "Basic Physics Series" about transverse and longitudinal waves, to be used in the classroom. Produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1953, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Quality of Life trailer (Reel AV 1988)
    A trailer reel of films depicting public welfare programs funded by the Ford Foundation in the 1970s including "The Walls Come Tumbling Down", "Vera and the Law: Toward a More Effective System of Justice", "Changing Work: American Workers in Sweden", and "Technology in Public Service."
  - Reading in an Audio-Lingual Program: Beginning Spanish (Reel AV 1422)
    Produced by the Foreign Language Department, Hicksville Schools, District 17, New York; footage of an elementary Spanish class doing exercises, repetition of phrases.
  - Reflections from Plane Mirrors (Reel AV 1788)
    Edited but unfinished footage of episode about optics and light, from educational series on physics. Probably from same series as others in this collection, produced by Educational Services Inc.
  - Refrigeration and Geysers, 1957 (Reel AV 1802)
    Episode from an educational series produced by Encyclopedia Britannica, "Physics: the Complete Introductory Course, filmed as taught in the public schools of Pittsburgh, PA". This lesson is from the section entitled "Heat", with Professor Harvey E. White, professor of physics, University of California. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica Films Inc.
  - The Religions of Asia, 1958 (Reel AV 1415)
    The final lecture in a series of 15 talks entitled "A Changing World in the Light of History," given by Arnold J. Toynebee at Washington & Lee University, Lexington VA. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica.
  - Reporter Der Windrose (Reel AV 2006)
    General note
    German
    Documentary film hosted by Peter von Zahn with a focus on the Ford Foundation and its philanthropic efforts.
  - Return of the Reluctant Prodigy, 1978 (Reel AV 1995)
    Documentary on Hungarian born American pianist Ervin Nyiregyhazi recording music for the International Piano Archive funded by a Ford Foundation grant. Copyright CTV Television Network 1978 Ltd.
  - Rural U.S.A. (Through Indian Eyes), 1952-1953 (Reel AV 1344A, Reel AV 1344B, Box 2, Dvd AV 1344A)